hello everyone
welcome to the active inference par at
all textbook group
welcome to cohort three
Our Journey Begins
here
it is uh January 25th 2023
and this is an onboarding and overview
meeting so as with all meetings it is
being recorded
we know that no single meeting time will
accommodate every single person's
schedule every time so live meetings of
this type are recorded and then later in
this day like 10 hours from now or
something there's the office hours
optional as everything is in Discord
and these meetings
um
are recorded they'll be available here
so for example you can see from cohort 2
there will be like a link for the video
recording
this first meeting is onboarding and
overview
so
the first part is going to be
going over the textbook group and the
structure of the coda which I know looks
large but it is possible to focus in and
Steward the parts that you're interested
in and not the parts that you're not
so I'm going to give an overview of the
structure of the textbook group in terms
of synchronous and asynchronous
participation and in the zoom chat
please feel free to ask any questions
you want just so that we can address
them
the goal here is to reduce your
uncertainty increase your confidence
around participating
there are so many ways to participate
and we want to welcome and accommodate
and encourage everyone coming from
totally different
learning preferences and backgrounds
so I'm starting on the very top left of
our Coda and the link has been put in
the chat and also note that I'm using
dark mode so Coda might look like that
but I'm using it in dark mode
welcome to the active inference
Institute
many people
um here in this room right now I I know
have been fundamental and with us for
years others this might be one of your
first times joining that's all great and
I'll put this link in the chat
the textbook group is one of many
activities that are ongoing at The
Institute so here we are in the portal
textbook group
and there's other Education and Research
oriented activities that you can explore
and and find out more about
but for now we're going to be focused on
the textbook group and we'll reach out
to other sources and places
as we need
the textbook itself is open source we
are talking about the textbook from
2022.
the active inference textbook by par
bazulo and Tristan and it's an open
source textbook which is awesome that
allows us to
facilitate us of course working in this
way and also it allows you to download
the textbook so you can download the PDF
right here and I know there's some other
efforts that some of you have
started involving like making it a
living textbook
the directory page and you can hide and
show
the sidebar sorry one second
the directory page has information on
different sections of the coda and what
you can find there
live meeting page summarizes when our
live meetings are happening
and we're specifically in cohort three
so here we are
uh this list is just Auto populated from
the names that people have put so let us
know
if you want anything to be changed just
activeinference gmail.com
and also this is a field that you can
edit if you want to add your desired
contact information it wasn't added for
anyone but if you want to put
contact me on this way at this time or
if you're interested in that like you
can add that here for connecting within
the cohort and then there's that cohort
3 live meetings page that has the the
date and time
of all of our meetings and that's where
the video recordings are going to be
placed as well
broadly today we're here to go on an
overview take any introductory thoughts
and questions
and also hear from each other like what
are we excited to learn and what is
going to motivate Us in this
optional but extremely exciting and
useful Quest that we're on
then we will have two weeks per chapter
the chapters are not super long so two
weeks is a good amount of time
to
give reading and or listening to it a
chance
take notes and we'll talk more about
what that can look like and be but on
the uh meeting for a given chapter
we're going to focus on that chapter and
sometimes again we'll reach into other
resources but we're gonna
focus our attention on the focal chapter
and then to a slightly lesser extent
other parts of the textbook because
people might have a question that like
oh that's going to come up in chapter
seven or that's going to come up in
chapter three and then
this textbook is not the only
star in the constellation of emerging
active inference literature and so
there's going to be many times where
we'll reference like other papers
uh other programs and especially we'll
reference a lot of the live streams the
several hundred paper oriented and model
oriented live streams that we've done at
the Institute and so many of the
critical papers and uh researchers we've
highlighted in these streams so it's
like a really awesome resource
okay
um as for onboarding and participation
so
these are all evolving documents and in
an evolving
open science Creative Commons space
so with our participation in synchronous
and asynchronous
Institute affordances like the Zoom room
and this Coda were agreeing and abiding
by
rules of General respect and also of the
um like open source status of what we're
collaborating on here
and we are students in the textbook
group we're focused on learning it's
going to lead many of us towards project
ideas and collaborations which were also
very excited to facilitate
we
expect and prefer and hope you to be an
Engaged learner
though there may be multiple types and
levels of novelty or frictions so
communicate early communicate often let
us know how we can improve things for
you
there's a lot of opportunities and
bandwidth to help you literally
specifically with what you want so make
it known and hopefully with this very
capable and diverse group we can make it
happen
we've also included some students
practices you can just click these
sections away if you're not
meeting them or not interested in the
moment but students practices like what
is it to really learn active inference
what are we really doing from a verb
perspective and so here are some
suggestions and some options
ranging from annotating writing
systematic reading
having Leisure Time making programming
constructions
adding questions adding ideas and
insights adding projects there's many
ways that we can participate and be
involved and if like you're finding
something that's exciting and engaging
for you and you feel like it's adding
value to your active inference learning
like let's add it other Learners may be
interested in it too
so
that's overall what participation is
like this is the pace or the Rhythm that
we'll be following in the sessions that
are weekly at this time we're going to
get in the next three months through the
first half of the book which is like a
lot of the conceptual and theoretical
underpinnings and then the second half
of the book is uh about a recipe for
modeling itself so you can see like
cohort 2 who meets actually an hour
before this if you ever want to join
welcome to same link
from September to November 22. we went
through chapter one through five and now
we're going through chapter six or ten
and so we'll do something similar like
from
May to August we'll go through chapters
six through ten again everybody can join
everything go through multiple times in
the beginning or however it's going to
work out in your life and practice
but we're going to be having this pace
with a recorded video meetings
going through chapters one through five
in the coming months
and then the prime if that is all you
have bandwidth for that's great
however to engage with the material on
your own time is really where the
learning is going to happen and some of
your edits and contributions on your own
time will be in this Coda as well in
sections that we'll look at others will
be in your own documents
so join when you can watch the video
recordings when you can
comment early comment often
let us know how we can help and improve
things
so let's go into first just any generals
questions on this and then we'll go into
like the textbook itself and how we use
Coda around the textbook
all right
in the textbook section itself
this textbook is
the first active inference textbook and
it's the first version of the first
active inference textbook there's a lot
of other
uh critical work
like vital work as well as skeptical
work
and Carl furston
who's one of the central researchers
in this field and part of azulo to
younger researchers who have worked with
friston have created this first version
of a first textbook published at the end
of March 2022 so about eight months ago
um
it's a big moment for our field and you
here are all some of the very first to
be going through this textbook which is
positioned as friston has said towards a
master student in computational
neuropsychiatry looking to apply this to
their own research that may literally
describe some of you others may have
quite a different context doesn't mean
it's going to be
um not fit for you in fact it's been
exciting to see how many different
backgrounds and people have resonated
with this textbook and with of course
all the related work so this is like
um a flag in the ground for active
inference but also this isn't a One-Stop
shop so anywhere that you're like I wish
they would have explained this or what
is the meaning of that like that is what
we're doing in this group
importantly this textbook doesn't have
any questions there's no um assessment
or
um basic comprehension questions
and that is also a huge aspect of what
our work is here
so
um to go through just some of these
pages and how we use the coda there are
some equations in this book you might
have noticed
how do we plan to understand and work
with these equations
recognizing everyone's different
capacities and preferences for equations
well one thing that we do is for every
equation and this work has been done by
previous cohorts so now we're in the
like improve phase not the first
construction phase
for every equation we have a screenshot
and a verbal description so anywhere in
the coda someone can be like I'm curious
about equation at 2.5
Mouse over it what is it oh okay okay
equation 2.5 cool well what but what is
it what does it mean
oh the variational free energy is ETC so
here's the natural language description
of these equations
I'm just muting people who are making a
little noise thank you
um
so
you'll gain familiarity with Coda and
how everything looks but when you see a
a canvas that you can pop out
you can find
um a natural language description and
it's not there for every single one so
these are like
the exact kind of contributions that
people can make that have extremely high
Leverage
anywhere that you can add a description
or add comments or notes add it in latex
those are like the kinds of local
improvements that in our group context
with like 30 plus future cohorts of us
here can be like actually
transformational I mean equation 2.5 is
one of the essential equations
how can we come to understand it well we
can have discussion we can ask questions
on it
we can do like what Jacob had previously
done like show how the lines of the
equation are related to each other so
there's an incredible amount of work
that we can do around improving the
equations and Coda facilitates us using
every row
as something that can be referred to
so that's equations we have figures
also every figure has been brought in
not everything is fully tagged or fully
described but
figure 2.2 oh there it is so we can use
it and refer reference to it as like
something stable and that's something
that we can ask questions about and so
on boxes and tables all of those have
been brought in
the code page this may or may not be
relevant for the first half of the book
for you depending on where you're at
with code
but we have a lot of active inference
code implementations
and um
we can go more into this as people want
to but there are a lot of code-based
implementations especially in Python but
also in Matlab and other languages for
people who want to like see
what it looks like in a program form and
something that we'll come back to again
and again it's just always a Nexus to
develop is we're going to be talking
about math natural language graphical
visualizations and art
programming philosophy like we're going
to have a lot of different things coming
together
there's no single path within active
inference or two active inference
people have difference backgrounds and
familiarities with different areas and
so maybe for one person it's like the
philosophical implications that are
exciting for you and then you'll come to
see the programming maybe somebody else
sees the programming adjacency and then
they'll come to be excited about the
philosophy or about how to visualize it
so we'll be moving across those domains
and
um
yes there is a facet of daunting scope
we're here in a new context and this is
an opportunity to
learn the way that we want to learn and
that is learning actively
in chapters notes and questions
um we have like some sections that if
you want to zoom in on a specific
chapter so here's like the table of
contents and then here's a the fine
scale table of contents with the
sections
um so somebody can say like I'm talking
about section at 1.4.2
again maybe that's like relevant and you
won't do that but we we do reference
different sections and then that makes
it okay that's what this section's about
here's what page it's on
um
within a given chapter like chapter one
there is a subset of questions that have
been asked on chapter one
and then also there's just other
discourse on these pages
and so we have those for all the
chapters and for the appendices
that's the textbook section it's
primarily just focused on stripping out
and re-formatting the material of the
textbook so that it can be referenced
and enriched to this extent like
everywhere that equation 2.5 is used
it's augmented by what we've added to
this table so
Mark once used many times
in the discourse on the textbook this is
like really where the creativity and the
generativity of our cohorts is going to
shine
we want to facilitate Active Learning
and a huge element of active learning is
this question based um perspective
so here's an overall questions table
and also there's a filter View
that will only be for our cohort
I
believe someone has already added a
bunch of questions for chapter one which
is awesome
um like
the questions are shown on the left and
you can just add by hitting enter and
just adding a new question down here and
then also you can pop up the answers in
discourse
so here it and also I'm using control
and plus or minus or control and scroll
to make Coda bigger or smaller that can
be quite useful
um
these questions that people have asked
range from basic
and testing comprehension of even very
yes or no or multiple choice
all the way to really the kind of
connections and relationships that are
the substance of having fluency and
comprehensive understanding of active
inference on through speculative
philosophy questions and open areas of
research
if each one of us here
added like one question per week
and refined
zero or a few questions of discourse
we would have a truly transformationally
different active inference learning
environment worldwide
and I don't think that's an
overstatement
there are not many groups working on
this textbook especially in this
collaborative capacity
the textbook doesn't have any questions
associated with it and we're very close
with the authors
we're going to have opportunities to use
what we're developing here broadly
and play a role in the future of active
inference education
that's one of the most important reasons
why adding questions and refining
questions is so critical like we've all
heard oh if you have the question then X
number of other people in this room or
lecture might as well
that is is and will be happening
globally
when we use the active inference
ontology which I'll come to after
showing the other sections we also can
leverage our questions in the discourse
on them
and in the live meetings
what we'll tend to do is focus on
questions that haven't been addressed
yet that have been upvoted as
interesting
like we'll just pop it open and let
people share and we'll all open up this
and we'll start taking down some
thoughts and questions and we're just
like getting it on
the page
being active making contributions it
doesn't need to be unified or
consistent in the initial framing but
these are the kinds of things that are
going to help people in their
synchronous and asynchronous active
learning
for this textbook and even Beyond
because a lot of these questions are of
course more General
ideas and insights is like if you just
want to lock in
idea or an Insight you had
and just crystallize that so that others
can see that oh chapter one I was like
oh
here's what this means
might be shocking for some might be
incomprehensible for some it's all good
just when you add in here
it becomes part of our Collective space
so I highlight questions a lot because
that is one of the most important ways
that we can
um
increment our understanding and go from
that like moment of friction or
uncertainty like what does that mean or
why doesn't they Define this or what is
this equation doing here what does that
figure mean it's like in that moment of
not understanding
make the choice to write down the
question
and our group will have an exponential
capacity but if everybody just wonders
about it and nobody writes a question or
augments the question then it's going to
be like we're all moving ahead linearly
the math learning group so um this is
active to the extent that people want it
to be
it was a suggestion and uh brought
forward by some of the participants in
the first cohort and in this little
subsection which again put it aside if
you don't want to
we really wanted to focus on the
foundational understanding of the math
that's one of the stickiest parts of
this field
and it is
also fundamental like the relationship
between surprise uncertainty in Hidden
states that relationship isn't
a poem it's beautiful but also there is
um
mathematics that underlies these topics
and we want it to be accessible and
rigorous for all so in this section
which again if somebody wants to like
Steward this math learning group
and bring together basic resources on
Matrix algebra on stochastic systems on
calculus or wants to write summaries
like some have done
that
come through
the um
sections
those are super useful
Jana any thoughts on being stuck or not
having questions
it's not required to ask questions so if
the expression that you have in response
to the material
is not question oriented if it doesn't
pose itself as a question
it's all good or as a question every
time it's all good
and so what is it that affords the
emergence of questions whatever it is
when it emerges feel free to capture it
if it emerges as something different
or even something ineffable or
non-active in that moment it's also all
good
add any other comments or feel free to
add things but like
number one imperatives to stay in the
game
stay engaged
and if we live to play another day we
advance our knowledge of active
inference and just for like a little
context this is something that would be
taught in a graduate school
optional seminar
for some of you that might literally
describe you but for those who are
stepping into something that from a
legacy perspective isn't what they would
be stepping into like
they're
at least I personally but I also hope
more broadly that The Bravery of that
could be understood
in project ideas
uh
participants have added various project
ideas
so contact these people or like add your
own ideas anything from doing audiobook
recordings to specific modeling
different educational
um possibilities
mathematical derivations so improving
like on one hand the rigor while we're
also working on the other hand
with accessibility keeping those
integrated
resources and may become relevant and
Ali contributed this initial table
it may become relevant to refer to other
resources so you'll find a lot of other
materials here
and in future textbook groups there's
like a feedback form
which will update at the end so that we
can give our feedback and then also like
uh if you want to share the link for
people who want to join future cohorts
and also just add like other feedback
like what can
a voluntary global
textbook Group B
how can we learn and apply
active inference
those are our some of our questions
um erada
are a few little typos and not just like
conceptual uncertainties but would
appear to be typos in the book
and also I'll note that on 17 UTC on
February 27th Thomas Parr will be
joining for live stream first author of
The textbook
so
in the next month
we will like highlight certain questions
that we want to surface when Thomas
joins it'll be like in a zoom just like
this
of course it'll be recorded
also if anybody like wants to join we
can talk about this in the coming weeks
but this is really awesome and unique
opportunity to ask Thomas directly
certain questions that we have so that
should be awesome okay last section and
then we'll go into more open uh uh group
discussion
this active inference tables section
has a few tables
uh that are going to be very useful
this is the active inference ontology
the active inference ontology is a a
central project since the earliest days
of active Institute
and one can see a little bit more about
it at this public site but there's also
more to it
um
the ontology at this point consists of
definitions and translations for a
reduced set of 74 core terms
and
a slightly broader list of supplemental
terms terms that are maybe not vital
like as prerequisites for understanding
octave but they're things that we might
mention like when we're learning and
this is again the public ontology site
so here we have
natural language definitions
four different terms just like a
dictionary uses natural language terms
to describe other natural language terms
that's what we're doing in the active
ontology
and just like being fluent in a language
means that you can recognize and use
the language understand what the
entities and the terms are the topics
and how they're related and why
this is a set of terms where if one is
fluent in perceiving and acting upon
them one has fluidity in active
inference
also the ontology
has translations so we have translations
into
um Spanish Portuguese French Italian
Czech Russian Hebrew Persian Chinese
Japanese
um Limited in Hindi and Turkish
if you want to improve one of these
ontology language translations
or you want to add another language that
is like an incredible service because
let's think back to that equation 2.5
when we see this blue text
these are ontology terms so the natural
language definition can pop up and when
we want to type something we can do like
at
generative model
we can then Translate
into other languages
very effectively
and have integrity across
representations and languages including
mathematics and non-mathematics but also
difference natural languages
so the ontology is how we're taking a
systems engineering approach to learning
and applying active inference
as this incipient ecosystem of learning
and application is really truly just
beginning we wanted to censor
accessibility and rigor from the
beginning and people are going to use
the ontology in different ways but
having it as a resource is already been
vital and for those who see this as like
a possible way to work as a way to
make
improvements to for example translations
and definitions
it's a big option
and we have a table here so that we can
reference it throughout because as
you'll see like questions use
where possible ontology tags
we're talking about minimizing surprise
now there still is a lot of
complexity around what Supply surprise
is but like this is a starting point
this is like something clickable and
interactable that we can always go
deeper into
um
last tables then we'll go into the
question section so here's the live
streams table
um or you can use the link here
here are the um
uh 200 plus live streams that we've done
all just highlight like live streams
are paper oriented so we've done 53
papers
so here you'll find a huge number of
relevant papers and if you could look up
like eco
okay here's some discussions on ecology
live stream are paper oriented guest
streams include a broad range of guests
in active and adjacent areas and like
always please feel free to suggest
anyone or make an introduction if you
want to see something highlighted model
streams focus on models and applications
of active inference like for example the
python implementation of Pi mdp which
we'll talk about
and then
um down on the bottom you'll see the par
pazula friston textbook and here you'll
see cohort ones videos so if you just
feel like watching cohort ones videos
then you can see like here's their
playlist
going through
um
and
here's just all the students with their
optional contact information so again
just to close the section within the
last 20 minutes we'll have uh anything
we want to ask or discuss
um
so um
overview provides some information on
active
textbook group
has information on our live meetings
textbook is mainly oriented around
focusing discussion on a given chapter
and on the contents of the textbook in
discourse we have questions ideas and
insights and project ideas
these are some places to make
contributions to
and then active inference tables just
hold some reference tables okay
I'll look at the questions in the chat
and then
um anyone who wants to raise their hand
or add something else in the chat okay
if I plan to engage asynchronously and
have questions on a chapter ahead of the
cohort 3 schedule where should I ask
them
great question so you can ask them also
in the questions table
here's cohort three questions
so they're all here if you have a
question on chapter three four five
just add it here
we'll get to it when we will get to it
um hope that addresses it but you don't
you're not limited to asking only what
we're going to discuss that week if you
have something on chapter three just add
it right here
thanks ever for asking answering it um I
was concerned the question would promote
discussion until the group made that
chapter
um it it can if it if like we're not
hyper only focusing on the the only the
text of the chapter but that is the
group regime of attention so it will
facilitate discussion when when people
do get there on their own time or in the
group
and you say I plan to implement some of
the active principles rather soon
by being here we are already all
implementing the principles and
anywhere that you can make your
contribution like we're all going to be
exploring and whittling away at this
forest in our own paths so just add it
and
it'll come into play
hope that addresses it um Lucas and then
anyone else
oh yeah I know you mentioned something
about listening to the book I did take a
look at it and it looks like there's a
lot of mathematical equations and graphs
like would you say that in order to have
the best experience it should be in a
physical copy to read rather than to let
them feel unaudible or something
great question few uh ways to to talk
about that like
uh
the audio version of the first chapter
was very easy introduction in the first
chapter which is what I made because
they didn't have equations
um
the natural language descriptions of the
equations one can imagine will be vital
for the audiobook
because one can then say Okay equation
2.5 and then read the equation
like this
we don't exactly have that yet and like
depending on how deeply one wants to go
into the math
like the zeroth level is like they just
put math here there are some other
section here
carrying on
the next level might be just like okay
this is about free energy
on some things what are those things
well okay you can go one level deeper
okay what is that function or what is
that functional okay one level deeper so
we're all like you can go down the
rabbit hole your whole life on two plus
two
and on the other side you can dance with
equations like this even if you don't
have a formal mathematical background
we're not
generating these equations were not par
or at all
we're just understanding what
to some extent they've put and then we
ask questions about like what the role
is of these equations and how they're
used and everything like that so
listening Maybe
a good experience but share your your
experience if if um you found listening
to it to be
like useful or found something locking
I'd like to find a way to articulate
mathematical equations audibly yeah
thank you like that is exactly what this
is about
and that can't be done
in a in even any automated way like
this and it's not the only way so if
someone has another idea about how to
audibolize equations that's also very
cool and creative but also like for
those who feel like they have the
capacity to just take a first stab
and you can select the text and then
just write like you know I'm not write a
comment I'm not sure
that's all good
but it's an example of how like one
contribution
can Leverage
people in other language communities who
are in different stages of learning and
applying
anyone else feel free to like raise your
hand
or just go for it
such small people are typing any
questions or thinking if they want to
raise their hand
um
two weeks per chapter
each time we have a discussion we'll
like go to that page
and we'll we'll first assess if we have
any questions that people like want to
discuss
and then
um
often in the first discussion or at the
end of the previous of the second
discussion of the previous section
we'll have kind of just like a look
ahead
or we look at what the section is
um
I'll give a quick
um overview on the structure of a
textbook so this could be seen at
chapter nodes and questions or it can be
seen in the table of contents
the book is separated into two parts
in the next three months in this cohort
three we're going to be focusing on the
first
five chapters
the first chapter is an overview it's
non-technical
has a lot of conceptual materials but
there are no equations or formalities
chapters two and three describe the low
road and the high road to active
inference it's a framing that we will
all come to know and love
the low road is kind of like the how
in terms of using the mechanics of
Bayesian statistics
and the high road is like the ultimate
why this is like the imperative of
persistence and the free energy
principle and the two roads meet in the
middle with octave inference which is
using
Bayesian statistics
to model and Implement that persistence
imperative from the free energy
principle all roads lead to octave
that's chapters two and three
chapter four having described the two
roads
to active inference
is the heart of active inference which
is about modeling
and it's about this specific type of
model called a generative model
the generative model is like the heart
or the kernel of active inference and
we'll get there chapter 5 then turns to
one of the areas where active inference
has been most characterized and studied
which is in mammalian neurobiology
and chapter 5 goes through a few neural
systems of mammals and talks about
active inference modeling in those
settings and then provides a table that
has citations to many other places that
active inference has been applied
so that's the conceptual half of the
book
is overview what's the big picture
what's the positioning what are we
talking about with active
what are the two roads to get there or
what two roads meet in active
what is the heart of active in terms of
generative modeling and then what is one
of the most critical areas that active
has been applied which is mammalian
neurobiology
the second half which is going to be
starting in a few months for this cohort
or people can show up one hour earlier
and check in with cohort 2 who's working
on the second half now
the second half starts
with a informal recipe for Designing
active inference models kind of like a
step by step but it's like a process or
recipe for this kind of modeling
so like
I'm gonna be like where's the modeling
where's the modeling it's like it it
it's
coming
and it's now for people who want to do
it
then chapter 7 and 8 describe a few
different important subtypes of
generative models
chapter 9 describes using data in
generative modeling
and chapter 10 is kind of like the
opposite of chapter one or the other end
of the bookshelf it's like summarizing
and giving an overview
there are some appendices that may be of
value to you
but
you may dive into those as their
reference in the text or no worries if
uh not
um
so that's kind of the broad picture
and the pacing that we're going to go
through
um
Kate thanks for the awesome question yes
if anyone has like python resources
uh putting them into code or resources
could be awesome here's like a bunch of
implementations
that we have
and in the recent
um Pi mdp stream
I'll put this link in the chat
this in the video description here's a
Google collab notebook
that doesn't need any tuning you can
just run this in your browser
and it is doing active inference so if
you want help with understanding like
the python Basics and the syntax of
python
um I'm sure many people can share
resources about that but like this
notebook
is awesome for actually working through
it and playing with different parameters
and in the first half of the textbook
we're building a lot of the conceptual
and formal understanding
so that when we're in the programming
we'll understand what these matrices are
and there isn't Just One path maybe
somebody wants to just work through this
and then
come to the formalisms later or work on
the philosophy and then come to the math
it's like there's just a million paths
so as long as we're in the gaming active
we're making it happen
um
okay any other thoughts or questions
okay just again raise your raise your
hand or or put it in the chat
um let's just do a little tiny look
ahead
next two weeks we're going to be
discussing chapter one the preface
um is written by Carl friston
it's just two pages long and it includes
this absolutely endearing confession
that Carl was not allowed to it was not
an affordance for Carl to write this
textbook
um
those who know may be familiar that his
writing style is very
um erudite and
so the book
it was not the desired Style
so that's just very nice by Carl
um but the preface doesn't really
um have any
big um pieces chapter one is the
overview
um yes thanks for those like all
different time zones coming through
um hopefully like the office hours at
the different time the recordings and of
course like if you want to suggest
another time that you could commit to it
may be possible to also add that
um but also
the synchronous activities are totally
optional
and
one's own reading or listening
contributions
are primarily on their own time
chapter one is an overview
it's introducing the main questions that
active inference is going to seek to
address that is the Target that they are
painting for this textbook is active
inference
as a unified principle for mind brain
and behavior
um and how can organisms persist amidst
environmental Exchange
that question is the heart of section
1.2
and we see a really
simplified version
of an action perception Loop
that we're going to be focusing on
agents
world
generative model agent generative
process World niche
doesn't only apply to mammals and
continents
it turns out that this formalization
of perception cognition
action and impact
is going to be immensely transferable
and composable
active inference is sometimes described
as a first principles perspective
and
it'll be awesome to hear more
discussions on like what people think
that means
but one way to think about it is like
this is kind of a first principles
approach
in terms of a how with base statistics
and this is like a first principles why
in terms of persistence as an imperative
there's the introduction of two
attitudes towards science neats and
scruffies
needs are seeking unification
scruffies embrace heterogeneity
and so do we want to have a unique
biological model let's have a journal
for every synapse let's have a a
different University for every single
follicle like at some point
we have
um composition
and harmonization not homogeneous
homogenization of the diversity of
biology
and so that neat scruffy dialectic
guides a lot of these discussions about
particulars in generals
the structure of the book
there's two parts to the book
these are aimed at readers who want to
understand active inference first part
that's us
and those who seek to use it for their
own research second part also that is us
we will get through both
the first part is going to introduce it
conceptually and formally
it's going to refer to some other
alternate theories of cognition
and so just to
um
plant the seed when people are asking
questions or even skepticisms or
critiques of active inference you can
ask yourself or them is this like a
critique of modeling in general like
would any usage of any model fall victim
to that criticism
which doesn't mean it's not valid it
just means that it's like in immensely
far-ranging critique
or is there a unique critique that is
being made of what we're actually
learning here
and it's not always immediately clear
the goal the first part is to provide a
comprehensive formal and self-contained
introduction to active inference its
main constructs and implications for the
study of brain and cognition
well we'll see if it is comprehensive
formal and self-contained
and where we have questions we can ask
where we want to add we can add
it's just the first version of the first
textbook
that's been in the niche for eight
months
and we can be part of that feedback loop
and make it happen
part one active inference in theory
that's the first five chapters this is
going to give some overviews on like key
terms that are going to come into play
why are we talking about surprise why
are we talking about adaptive control
why are we talking about the action
perception Loop
here's that figure the two roads to
active inference High Road starting on
the top right free energy principle
Road starting on the bottom left base
theorem
description of the high road and low
road which are going to be chapters two
and three
chapters two and three
chapter two low road chapter 3 High Road
chapter four
active inference formally that's where
we're going to get to the generative
model what is the generative model
what is generative modeling that is the
heart of active inference like the
linear model is at the heart of linear
modeling and the generative model is
going to be at the heart of active
inference modeling
and then chapter 5 is going to move from
the generative model in the abstract to
a setting where generative models have
been applied
at this point the most densely in
literature which is mammalian
neuroscience
here are some of the key differences
between active and Alternate Frameworks
the unity of perception and action in
terms of a shared imperative to minimize
free energy
the accommodation of planning and policy
selection
censoring sensory data
diverse cognitive operations attention
memory anticipation
conceptualized as inference over
generative models
consistent with the Bayesian brain
hypothesis
perception and learning as active
processes
action as goal oriented
which has many deep roots in cybernetics
and the biological plausibility
of different constructs
part two active inference in practice
check out that but we're not going to
focus on it immediately
and 1.5
this chapter is just summarizing the
first half of this book
and the second half
previewing the perspective that will be
unpacked
the books divided into two parts
understand and use
they hope it will persuade readers that
active inference offers not only a
unifying principle
under which to understand Behavior but
also a tractable approach to studying
action and perception in autonomous
systems
so
it's about 14 pages long
we have two weeks to discuss it
so we'll be able to surface many
Reflections and sensitivities that
people are having
two
chapter one
that
concludes our first meeting
following this meeting the recording
will be posted in like as a unlisted
YouTube video here
and um
actually immediately following this
meeting
over in the Discord
uh which I'll copy the link in we're
just gonna
hang out and just have education open
hours so it's gonna it's kind of
convenient
um if you want to continue just the
discussion on the textbook or learning
or education so
thank you all for joining
I will close the recording and looking
forward to seeing you next week
thank you bye